[Music]
Hey
good morning good afternoon good evening
to everyone this is another edition of
our with sunny researcher Club today
we're talking about Boltzmann evaluating
privacy using entropy metrics just work
done entirely by Laurel or Mt
it's all available on github and of
course we link all of the work that we
go through on our wasabi research Club
github which is just down below just to
remind ourselves where we are we did a
bunch of coin shuffle plus plus cash
Fusion and we talked about principles
and privacy talking about best practices
and how we go about thinking about
designing privacy for anonymity networks
we talked about Koh enjoy Sudoku last
week and this week we're doing Boltzmann
when the end of this video hopefully
we'll resolve what we will be reading
next week last week we talked about the
coin joint pseudo paper which tried to
be anonymized flawed coin joints done by
shared coin which was a blockchain
info implementation which simply took
transactions than merge them and the way
that the D anonymization attack happened
is that as
one sec guys I'm just trying to know yes
it's gone oh yes I don't know is this
better
yes yes excellent okay so moving right
along so we talked about how if two
transactions are merged together then
there is some uncertainty about how we
could be anonymized the merged
transaction but if we wanted to do
naanum eyes the more transaction so here
on the Left we have transactions on the
right we have the merged together as in
one transaction what we really need to
do is figure out how to make the inputs
and the outputs match in sums
just like this and we keep trying until
we find a valid partition of a
transaction so here we have an example
of a partition of a transaction where we
can break up the original transactions
to smaller transactions this is this is
the most important thing that we've
talked about now I think in four
separate times and I'm gonna simplify it
which is that if when we talk about how
anonymous or how private a transaction
is we can take any particular input and
any other input or output it doesn't
really matter you can take you know a
handful of inputs you can take a handful
of outputs you can take any partition
you want and you can ask how likely is
it these partitions this these these
components are related and the magic
formula which is on the Left written
clearly in math terms on the right in
English terms it's simply given a
particular combination you find all of
the possible possible valid partitions
that include that particular combination
and then you divide by all possible
valid combinations so for example
if you are concerned about a specific
transaction and you want to ask is input
for an output six in to what extent are
they related how likely is it that
they're in the same transaction or you
could do it you can find all the
partitions where I four and O six are a
part of that and that could be the
number twelve there could be 12 those in
total and you divide it by the total
number of possible valid combinations of
any kind which could be hypothetically
267 and then you get yourself a number
like four point four nine percent and
you can do this for any input against
any output or anything of that nature
and two big things we talked about
subset sum is the ability to do exactly
what we just talked about finding inputs
and outputs that match in the size and
the bail number is the number of
possible ways a set can be partitioned
and we know that the bail number grows
very quickly and the subset-sum problem
is computationally very difficult for
large numbers so today we're talking
about something different which I'll
admit is a very philosophically
interesting topic it's a it's a very
abstract way to think about things but
it's the concept of entropy so a cursory
look for the definition we get a few
different ways that we use this word it
will see the exact way where it should
be in the word cook purposes of coin
joints but a one example for example
thermodynamics which is the likely thing
you've heard is that the quantitative
measure of the amount of thermal energy
not available to do work which is kind
of interesting kind of an abstract thing
to say another thing you might have
heard as well as the measure of disorder
or randomness in a closed system another
thing you might have heard is and this
is actually the one that's somewhat more
important is the measure of loss of
information in that transmitted message
but we're actually concerned about
something a bit different than exactly
that but similar enough that entropy is
valuable so one way we look at entropy
is we can you know
I was thinking a lot about visualization
of entropy there are many good ways to
think about entropy but on the right we
have a solid where all the atoms are
very close together and on the Left we
have a gas and in the middle we have a
liquid as you see here the atoms are
spread out and more I guess you could
say random and so we would say that on
the right we have low entropy and on the
left we have high entropy but maybe a
better way of saying this this is what
my father told me and he said he's a
physicist he said that it's imagine your
own bedroom and a state of low entropy
is one where all everything in your room
is very neat and clean and organized all
the shirts are together all the pants
are together all the pillows are
together everything is very very
partitioned and naturally as you live in
your room and if you don't do the work
to to maintain this this cleanliness
then things tend to just sort of spread
out and go all over the place you have a
book on your bed you have the sock in
your your the bathroom all sorts of a
mess and that's what we call high
entropy and there are some some
interesting laws these aren't exactly
the laws of thermodynamics because they
don't matter for our state but there are
two things to consider the first to
consider is this principle of
conservation of energy which for us
matters because we deal with with
conservation of energy in it in Bitcoin
namely that Bitcoin is always conserved
in the transaction and the second is
that the state of a closed system is
that it tends towards a higher entropy a
good way of imagining this is that if
you take a bottle of cologne and you
spray it in in a closed room as the time
goes on the cologne is not going to
exist in one place that the particles
the molecules of the cologne are going
to go throughout the entire room as
opposed to concentrate in one area where
they started in the bottle of cologne so
as I said before with Bitcoin energies
conserve the left hand and the right
hand must always match so when we have a
change of state in which
transaction transactions change the
state of Bitcoin ownership remembers to
the other
we know that coins are always conserved
so that's kind of a cool remark and and
now we're talking about something very
different but but but very interesting
which is Shannon entropy so Shannon
entropy has to do with information
theory and much less to do with physics
and the concept of Shannon entropy and
it shares intuition with Boltzmann is
that is that it's thinking about how to
explain this okay so suppose you need to
uncover a certain English word or five
letters you managed to obtain one letter
for example the letter E this is useful
information that the letter is Coenen
English this provides little information
if another hand a letter that you
discovered is je the least common letter
in English this search has been more
narrow and obtained more information I
think a good way I watched an excellent
20 minute presentation specifically on
entropy and I think a good way to
condense it is it it it it's it's the
number of the the number of questions
you would have to ask binary questions
you would have to ask to get to the
information that eat that you want to
know but is currently unknown so it's
also been abstract but will only read
that so we define the Shannon entropy of
a a piece of information a as these sum
of probabilities of all the different
possible states it's lucky for us that
in when we're talking about coin joints
we don't value one type of coin went
over the other we don't value one or
addition as being more likely as another
therefore we don't need to work with
those probabilities but this is the
technical definition of entropy and and
so for the case of what Lorant brought
up is he's
define entropy as as that has log2 of
the number of possible ways you can
partition a transaction so the question
you might ask is why is it log 2 why is
it for example not the natural logarithm
which is which is almost log 2 but it's
not quite why is it not log 10 well it
turns out it's love 2 because in
information theory looking we're
concerned with information being
represented as bits so it makes sense
that when we when we say something has a
Shannon entropy of 2 what we're really
saying is that if you could ask to
binary questions and get valid answers
you would know the original information
so the information is distorted in such
a way where you have to ask to binary
questions that's what the the number the
entropy number of 2 would be and
likewise the number of 3 would be that
you have to ask three sequential
questions binary questions in a row to
get the valid original information
Lorant gives some examples so in this
case you gives an example with 6 5
inputs and one output and because there
are no ways to consider this transaction
apart from all of the funds moving 202
there's only one possible case so the
entropy is zero in other words we
wouldn't have to ask any binary
questions because it's already into
turistic week so it would be easy for
anyone to know who gave money to o2 and
what happened here here's an example
where it's a little bit less clear so so
now there are two possible
interpretations of this transactions
what are the two possible
interpretations well here's the first
one maybe yellow gave money to himself
and then green gave money to herself or
it's one individual and they gave money
to themselves those are the two possible
cases and so we have an entropy value of
1 and lastly we have the example number
3 where we have two inputs four outputs
here's the first case here's the second
case
because the values are the same it's
like a coin joint we can see that you
can replace those two values and then of
course we have the obvious case where
it's all in one individual because we
have three cases we have an entropy of
one point five eight five because there
are three cases okay so we're on rent
receipts to define a few terms which are
interesting intrinsic entropy being the
value computed without any additional
information no additional relation so
consider the transaction outside of the
blockchain
so this is what his his script was doing
when he was just taking one transaction
at a time and calculating it the actual
entropy is the value computed
considering additional information on
watching so you know was there any
address for use was did the output then
get merged with another output that's
revealing common ownership and then
there's max entropy which is kind of an
interesting one as well the value
associated with a perfect transaction in
coins run with equal outputs and inputs
that are similar to the original
transaction and he calls these this type
of transaction tuples I believe 100%
sure and so from there he says that
wallet efficiency is the intrinsic
entropy minus the max entropy expressed
in bits and the blockchain efficiency is
the actual entropy minus the max entropy
and I guess the reason why he says this
is because the wallets cannot really
know what the actual entropy is because
wallets are non blockchain analysis
companies they don't have very
sophisticated tools on hand so the wall
efficiency is purely looking at the
intrinsic versus the max and watching
efficiency is actual versus Max so his
own results in print in in doing this
was he investigated 97 million
transactions computed entropy for 98
when 59% of them and was not able to
process 1.4 1% and the reason why is
pretty
obvious because everything we've talked
about in the in the past few weeks with
the coin joints in Oakland but having to
find all of the partitions of a of a
coin joint it becomes a very expensive
task when you talk about many inputs and
many outlets so as we stop cried gopher
for many many transactions so of the
transactions who did process eighty five
point four seven had a null at repeat
which means that there was no question
about the inputs and outputs being
linked fourteen wanted each you had
entropy of greater than one so they were
ambiguous transactions and one point
eight nine percent had an entropy of
greater than one point five eight five
as good or better than a corn joint so
yeah yeah I think I think we'll probably
leave it there for now and open up Thank
You Aviv after your presentation I got
more confused of least important
questions but let's let's try to let's
try to figure that out because I'm not
sure we looked at the exact same source
I was looking at the gist what did you
look at yes yes yes all right
so yeah I am I was mainly concerned of
the first one the last two way I just
just went through but I get the
transaction the actual data is in the
last two is innately what you cited here
no I think I was mostly focused on the
first one as well I mean I could be
wrong when everything I just talked
about was the first one okay so the very
first thing about the first one is that
it so that the number and you know the
number of valid sub mappings
you hear in your presentation added it
to D added the full mopping right when
when it's only
one person transferring money to himself
but he actually did not add it to the
calculation of n is that is that what
you remember exactly okay one more time
so so the transaction itself when it's
just one person it is he did not add it
to the calculation of the end you know
the number of valid sub mappings oh oh
he absolutely did
okay I mean even Adam gives unaltered it
under the geese that that should be
added anyways it's a not important
question I think it's a it's it's better
to add two because that's definitely a
possibility anyway and another thing is
that I I was immediately assuming that
it was Shannon entropy too but then I
noted it under the gist under comment
and he did not seem to know what I was
talking about why am I talking about
Shannon and why am i calling each a non
entropy and I was like okay I just
missed remembered I I didn't know why I
was assuming that but now in your
presentation you actually went through
it that hey this is actually the Shannon
entropy do you know is this the Shannon
entropy or or or do you know what where
my confusion is coming from here yes so
it would not make sense for it to be any
other kind of entropy other than Shannon
entropy so the problem is that entropy
is used for very different things
in science and Shannon entropy is
concerned with information theory
and that's what we're concerned with as
well so you know if it was really
Boltzmann when we use the Boltzmann
constant because he didn't use
Boltzmann's constant okay that's that's
an interesting question would be nice
about or would be here good answer to
that anyway I think these are the least
important questions here do you guys
have have anything or or should I go
forward okay go ahead then Adam Gibson I
have my own opinion on on this what I'm
going to ask you guys but Adam gives on
was critiquing it that well what about
pay too and point transactions and what
about all the different kind of
interpretations of all the transactions
it does not seem to toward I mean
did you guys read that conversation and
what do you think about that so I did I
didn't read the conversation and I think
that it's it's not part of the scope of
what this what this paper is trying to
achieve so I don't think it's important
so for example if we knew that 1% of the
transactions were paid joins then we
would have to add that as a caveat
then we have this tool over here but
then in 1 percent of the time you have
to use a completely different tool to
understand what's going on so I don't
think it changes very very much anyone
else
yes I think that you need to assume
something when you analyze the
transaction otherwise there are no way
to to get any conclusion for example if
you say okay there is an aristocrat says
that the inputs belong to the same owner
the same wallet yes I could say no
that's not necessarily true so that
doesn't mean you have to discard or
reject the heuristic the realistically
system is still valid because most of
the times the inputs belong to the same
guy right even when could be the
opposites attract so you need to assume
something right
otherwise the transaction can have lots
and lots and lots of interpretation even
the most simple and obvious transaction
could have a lot of interpretations yeah
and that's exactly why I don't actually
understand how any blockchain analysis
is like valid considered valid I have an
even stronger opinion in defense of this
research because as far as I understand
it just doesn't matter because this
research wants to break down big
transactions into small individual
transaction parts and all the heuristics
all the different kind of
interpretations can come only after the
parts the specific sub mappings so you
can only apply them to D Sub Pop ings
you cannot apply any interpretation
cross Harry sticks even with pay to
endpoint ban the receiver
participates in the coin join itself
that would be that would still give a
valid input and outputs sub mappings
like a subset some right like like the
same sum on the input side with receiver
and the sender contributing to the same
contributing with different inputs but
that still gives the exact same subset
on the output amount so I believe Harry
sticks and different interpretations of
the transaction just not only is not
efficient to to be part of this research
but it just doesn't need to be because
the subsets are just independent
concepts from that they do you guys
agree or or am I miss taking here Lucas
set it right you just you have some
assumptions and this works perfectly if
you just assume a few things pay join is
outside of the scope so you just say
that you're concerned with only things
that meet those assumptions yeah but my
point was even if you assume pay join
the the subset sums the volleyed sub
mappings don't wouldn't change with that
assumption you wouldn't be able to
incorporate that assumption because it's
instead of the sender merges two queens
it's the sender and the receiver merges
together two coins in the same subset
sum and you know it's it these these
heuristics these interpretations don't
happen cross sub mappings so III at
least I cannot come up with any such
example where when these interpretations
could mess with this scheme itself
that's my point here
I think I understand what you mean yeah
I agree
could you explain it because I it it's
obvious that I'm not explaining it no I
barely understand what you mean sir I
don't think I can do any better job all
right I mean why do you mean like the
the amounts of outputs and I mean it's
some way you like clear from that with
such a little amount of inputs and
outputs that I don't know it's like yeah
I'm not sure I probably can't explain it
any better than you did
for example this I you and me
participating in a paid to end point
transaction I put in one Bitcoin you put
in to Bitcoin and three Bitcoin comes
out to you now if we put this pay to end
point transaction into a coin join in
itself that that does not that that
still of all its submarines the one
Bitcoin input to Bitcoin input and the
three Bitcoin output that's a completely
valid sub mappings what voids one is
looking for so it won't be like like I
put in one Bitcoin input you put into
Bitcoin input and somehow you only get
back to Bitcoin output unless I get back
on Bitcoin output right so the the the
input sums and output sums of every sub
mapping has to add up to the same amount
and and that's that's why I don't think
this is important
anyway I understand what you're saying
now you're saying that you could still
use Boltzmann to parse
all the page wines that are separate in
the coin join and you can figure that
out later if that's what you mean to say
yes like it exactly yeah I agree and now
I have two topics left out one is that
is a nice one you know let me let me
read but as illustrated by conjuring
pseudo who attack this metric face to
detect privacy leaks occurring at the
lower level of specific inputs and
outputs and we just talked about
conjoined Sudoku last time and it's it's
interesting that you know it's it's
claimed but the research was never real
history this is the classic example and
I was saying that this was actually
cited by so many places and never really
looked into it that much anyway the
other thing is not suck we we always
keep coming back to nap sock and I think
this might be the very best time to come
back to nap sock here because if you
look at the entropy here is the log 2n
that only depends on the number of valid
sub mappings right nothing as n is the
number of valid sub mappings and the
look to is is there so so this is what
only depends on but we can improve upon
it a lot because knapsack actually gave
us a mathematical model on on what s to
look at knapsack not all only looks at
the number of total valid sub mappings
but the input input links input output
links output and the output output links
links means like probability of links
and you talked about this miss Aviv and
and this is this is the final picture
here right like like you have to
incorporate the these links between each
other oh my god the baby is crying
because I'm talking too loud so let me
say it quickly so you have to
incorporate these links into your
entropy calculation and you get a much
more accurate anthropometric with with
with incorporating the knowledge in
knapsack that's my point
I have a question that I think Lucas
might know but I'm still confused as to
why using log to make things valuable
for us like like yeah I'm not I'm not
seeing the utility of this of this of
this approach I mean it's the same as we
talked about before it's exactly the
theory that I have in this slide right
here what's you know what's the big you
know how are we gonna make use of the
fact that we're applying log to to the
because the number of combinations that
you have is 2x I don't know how to say
this is to today and exponential you
know to and so if if you have the number
of combinations you applied a lot of the
love to and and then you get the
the this number that gives you how many
bits of entropy you you have in that
transaction are you satisfied with this
answer well I'm just trying to think
into my head how I'm gonna use log 2 in
terms of terms of maximum solely or
usually how about entropy of 3 and
entropy of 4 because there were nine
partitions in one and and well I think
I'm not doing the calculation but
anyways the point is if I have an
entropy of let's say two and four does
that mean it's twice as private is that
the idea here so it's I don't know why
lock to but I I have a good feeling
about the logarithm part of the log for
sure because if you think about it that
you have five inputs and five outputs
and let's say you get ten combinations
and if you have 10 inputs antenna
outputs then you you don't get 20
combinations but you get something like
100 or something like exponential number
of combinations and but ultimately the
links between the inputs and outputs and
input input output outputs are are not
that so so there is only 10 inputs and
10 outputs so that there cannot be so
the number of combinations may be
exponential but you don't gain that much
more privacy just because the number of
combinations exponential so let's throw
a logarithm at it and actually that's
what I thought how how the Shannon
entropy came to light to that you know
it just just Oh
let's throw a lot
because it seems right III thought it
was an intuitive thing but now I I don't
know but anyway the logarithm is very
intuitive here because he with this you
can compare two transactions more
accurately of course it's just an
estimation but but more accurately does
that make sense
not exactly I mean you know you could
also divide by 10 right I understand
that you're saying that the number of
partitions grows exponentially but you
have to convince me why the privacy
doesn't grow exponentially what you're
seeing right now is the privacy is
growing linearly as your your subsets
are growing exponentially yes
not exactly linearly but more like
linearly yes because the number of
participants aren't growing
exponentially so it's it's not fair to
say that that well it had ten
participants in this transaction and and
so your anonymity growth exponentially
right but the efforts that you need two
or ten you miles
they grow exponentially I mean Mountain
View power you need to spend to
randomize so if we look at this so maybe
cross a financial aid room yeah that I
would say that's another question here
because here the assumption is that it
can be the anonymous no matter what is
the number
it can be the anonymized that's why
Botsman cannot be computed to to larger
coin joints so so so we are operating
under the working assumption that
everything can be the anonymized in no
time and there is no computation or
complex
team worked here
I would love to explain more this to you
guys but the baby's crying and it's
because I'm too loud sorry okay so why
don't we get more questions anyone else
have a question they want to ask can you
change the slides I don't know which one
was it I had a question about it a
little bit more today yeah this one can
you explain a little bit more about
these results yeah sure so Lauren took
roughly a hundred million transactions
and tried to use try to use try to break
them down subset-sum do they figure out
all the partitions and then compute the
entropy right so find in for every
transaction and of course most of the
transactions it's easy to do this so
that was the case from 98.5 9% of
transactions and some transactions it
was it was too time-consuming and so of
the ones that were computed a majority
had no entropy which means there was no
other subset apart from just the
transaction itself 14.5 2% so it is very
specific thing you wanted to ask about
know exactly the what is these the the
last two things
exactly so 14.5 2% had an entropy of
equal to or greater than one so that
means that the transaction had two
possible interpretations because log 2
of 2 is 1 right and then 1.8 9%
had an entropy of greater than 1.5 A's
so at least three interpretations or
more okay yeah I got it now thanks
Monica so we would say that eighty five
point forty seven percent times ninety
eight point fifty nine percent is the
total number of transaction which is a
very large number it's likely about
eighty percent of transactions that were
that were in the pool had zero
protection completely deterministic okay
thanks yeah that explained by questions
so you know what I was thinking about
like the whole meaning of this entropy
thing I guess I kind of get it if you
have a value of your entropy of one that
means that you have to ask one binary
question in terms of figuring out the
correct mapping and if you have an
entropy value of two it means you have
to ask to binary questions and so forth
if you have three then you have to ask
three minor questions and I guess this
this does make sense with transactions
that really do involve only one person
or or two people but I'm not sure how I
would apply at scale so so for example I
don't see the benefit of applying it to
a wasabi coin join I'm not sure I mean I
say see the benefit I think the
anonymity said is a much clearer
heuristic it's Laura seventy-three yes
summer a t-shirt okay
a sense to apply to the possibly
transactions but you can't because it's
computationally infeasible but it would
be really interesting to see what are
the results there okay yeah I agree
yes yeah wait I am happy and the entropy
yes there is this entropy of the
transaction right and there and then
there is this level of Nikki ability
let's say that you show us that is is
interesting too but also in the second
part of this gist collection the visa
matrix of I don't remember the name but
it's a matrix of let me when we find it
and a link probability matrix of a
transaction the if I understand I I
didn't read it carefully
yes but I think it is a matrix that for
each input and each output calculates
all contains the the probability of a
link between the input and the output I
can be ground because again I didn't
read it yet but it it could mean it
makes sense to me so I think it is it is
a good a good tool to to apply against
well I think this is what the
the thing this thing is already done
okay I mean I I can be long but it would
be interesting to do in fact we can we
can select one of the smaller muscle
transactions and see if it is possible
to to run this is to should
three-dimensional matrix because you
need the input input links the input
output links and output output links has
lots of paper says it oh yes very good
but
computationally I think that's extremely
expensive now it is it isn't expensive
it isn't more expensive at all because
what man relies on identifying the sub
transactions and the links between input
inputs inputs and output outlets are
calculated by looking at which sub
transactions that things are in and
divided by the totals of transactions so
computational work here is identifying
that sub transactions or the sub
mappings same thing and it's not
calculating the links that is the first
thing here
yeah so you got it
yeah sure oh by the way you don't have
to be in ASMR mode too you can shout
what paper would you like to to look
into next week
okay so if you don't give ideas then I'm
going to see a few papers and just shout
which one would you like so okay
for me
researchers in entropy Wonderland the
review of the entropy concept
a crypto economic traffic analysis on
the bitcoins lightning Network
[Laughter]
vikon joy as used in dark coin does not
bring food anonymity
yeah yeah it sounds interesting
yeah next Harry sticks on Bitcoin
privacy Wikipedia page next beepers from
a blockchain analysis company it's not a
paper it's just whatever we choose next
topological analysis of the Lightning
Network next by I'm not an entropy I
think this would be very similar to the
anonymity loves company our paper may be
a little bit more technical but what
similar philosophical one I have no idea
but it that one sounds insensitive
interested to me too I agree ok did I
sense that everyone agreed on that who
did not agree on that I I vote for that
too I think that's very interesting
all right I guess that settles it
next week we are going to
peer review the paper by I'm not an
anthro pissed okay thank you guys for
the party spirit you and for your
patience for listening to be in hit
summer mode okay thank you guys thank
you thank you hey guys you know the
recent story about someone who calls and
by phone and a boy a little boy say hi
the so the the the update the caller say
hey boy
it's your man now she's not she's busy
okay and your dad he's not available
he's busy and what are they doing they
are looking for me okay